[Music]
dark green leafy vegetables are packed
with a brain antioxidant called lutein
and so increasing our greens intake
could be an important public health
strategy for reducing the risk of visual
or cognitive impairment
lutein is the dominant dietary pigment
in the retina of the eye as well as the
brain and so not surprisingly that
macular pigment the concentration of
lutein in the center of your eye called
the macula was found to be significantly
correlated with levels in the brain
which may explain the link
between how much of these greens
nutrients you can see in the back of the
eye and cognitive function the neural
protection is soon to be because lutein
is such a powerful antioxidant but it
also has
anti-inflammatory properties
this relationship between lutein and
another greens nutrient called
zeaxanthin and visual and cognitive
health throughout the lifespan is
compelling but that was based on
observational studies where you observe
that higher lutein levels and brain
function seem to go together but you
don't know if it's cause and effect
until you put it to the test
could lutein and zeaxanthin be
supplemented
as part of a lifestyle intervention to
both improve brain function and reduce
the probability of slipping into
dementia
the reason everyone's so excited about
the possibility is because of the
hopeful data from eye health studies
that have convinced many
ophthalmologists to start recommending
people start increasing their lutein and
zeaxanthin intake to prevent and treat
macular degeneration a leading cause of
age-related vision loss
you don't have to take pills though
adding as little as 60 grams of spinach
a day for a month that's like one fifth
of a 10 ounce package of frozen spinach
can significantly boost macular pigment
in most people
and it's not just good for treating
diseased eyes a randomized
placebo-controlled study found that
these greens goodies can improve visual
processing speed in young healthy people
that's like when you're trying to hit a
fastball and your body has to start
reacting before you even consciously
register it with real world benefits
outside the major leagues improving for
example visual driving performance
okay but what about cognition
a randomized double-blind civil control
trial of adults average age 73 given the
equivalent of about a half cup of days
of cooked kale or a full cup of cooked
spinach and got significant improvements
in cognitive function compared to those
randomized to the placebo may even work
in young adults too average age 21.
daily supplementation with the same
amount of lutein and zeaxanthin not only
increased their macular pigment but
resulted in significant improvements in
brain function spatial memory reasoning
ability and complex attention
have they ever tried putting whole foods
to the test
hard to get americans to eat greens
every day but
not so hard to get them to eat guacamole
this study tests the effects of the
intake of avocado on cognition a
six-month randomized controlled trial
what was the control
one avocado a day or
a potato or a cup of chickpeas and those
in the avocado group had a significant
improvement in cognitive function
but to the avocado board's chagrin
so did the tater and chickpea group
that's the problem with having healthy
placebos maybe they should have used you
know iceberg lettuce or something
what about the impact on the cognition
of those who really need it alzheimer's
disease patients
their vision got better that's good but
no significant changes in cognitive
function
now it's possible that eating whole
foods like dark green leafies might have
worked better
than just the pigments in pill form
yes oxidation and inflammation appear to
be key to both alzheimer's and macular
degeneration but neither disease seems
particularly amenable to late stage
treatments that's why
prevention is the key reducing oxidation
inflammation in the earliest stages may
be our most promising approach
[Music]
you